Guide to the Wayne A. Wiegand research files.
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Wayne A. Wiegand research files.
Wiegand, Wayne A., 1946-
5 linear ft. (4 record cartons)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1595
9070873
Research files of library historian Wayne Wiegand.
Biographical Note
Wayne Wiegand, library historian and Melvil Dewey biographer, received his B.A in history from University of Wisconsin-Oshkosh in 1968 which he followed with an MA in history at the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee in 1970. As a graduate student in history he became interested in libraries and upon completion of his M.A. he went on to receive his Masters of Library Science at Western Michigan University and finally a Ph.D. in history at Southern Illinois University.
He served as a librarian for a number of years before starting to teach in library schools. He served on the faculty of the College of Library Science at the University of Kentucky and the School of Library and Information Studies at the University of Wisconsin–Madison and, finally, as Professor of Library and Information Studies and Professor of American Studies at Florida State University. While at the University of Wisconsin he founded the Center for the History of Print Culture in Modern America.
He has written several books on print culture and library history, including a biography of Melvil Dewey and the Encyclopedia of Library History.
Scope and Content
Collection contains card files related to Wiegand's research on Melvil Dewey and American Library history.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 2 series
Series I: Chronological Files on Melvil Dewey
Series II: Research Files, by Subject
Subjects
American Library Association.; Dewey, Melvil, 1851-1931.; Library science--History.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Wayne A. Wiegand Gift, etc. 10/21/2011 2011.2012.M040
- Chronological Files on Melvil Dewey
  The Chronological files on Melvil Dewey are research files on index cards assembled by Wiegand while researching his biography of Melvil Dewey. The cards include biographical information about Dewey, as well as quotes and citations from primary and secondary sources.
  - 1851-1976 (Box 1)
  - 1876-1885 (Box 1)
  - 1886-1892 (Box 1)
  - 1893-1896 (Box 1)
  - 1896-1902 (Box 2)
  - 1903-1905 (Box 2)
  - 1905-1914 (Box 2)
  - 1915-1929 (Box 2)
  - 1930-1946 (Box 3)
- Research Files
  The Research Files contain index card files about a variety of topics related to American library history. A significant portion of the material is related to the history of the American Library Association.
  - American Library Association Bibliography and Historiography (2 card Boxes) (Box 3)
  - American Library Association members alphabetical file (Box 3)
  - Research Files on American Libraries, (4 card Boxes) (Box 4)